Hello, this is Dr. Dong Zang.
In this lecture, we'll discuss
the metabolism of lipoproteins.
And here's the learning
objective slides.
And hopefully, the
slides will help you
or guide you how to
study this lecture.
First, we want to
discuss the structures
of different
lipoprotein particles.
And as you probably know,
all the lipids from the
diet, including triacylglycerols,
in short for TAG,
or triglycerides, in short
for TGs, right? So these
molecules have very long
hydrophobic tails, and so therefore
they're not very soluble
in the aqueous solution.
and similarly with the
cholesterols right as you
remember that the
cholesterols has the four very
hydrophobic grains and again
they're not very soluble
in the aqueous solution
but blood is more or less
aqueous solution right
so therefore the body
have to figure out a
way to how to transport
all these lipids whether
they from dye or they
from endogenous synthesized
to different tissues
and organs so the strategy
that the body use is
using these so-called
lipoprotein particles right
so these lipoprotein
particles are basically
a kind of complex of
a variety of lipids
and a variety of proteins
and just the protein part
of the particle and they
are also called apoproteins
right so as illustrated
in this diagram these are
lipoprotein kind of the
ball shape structures and on
the shells the shells are
made up of the phospholipid
right here's the diagram
of the phospholipid and
they all have a polar head
right again you know like
the aqueous environment
but they also have long non
-polar tails so these
molecules are also called
amphipathic molecules because
they like both the aqueous
environment as well as the
hydrophobic environment
for the hydrophobic lipids
including cholesterol and
other lipids and they are
get packaged inside the
ball of the phospholipids
right as you recall that
cholesterol also has a
little hydroxy group which
is hydrophilic right so
therefore the hydro hydroxy
group of the cholesterol's
kind of facing the aqueous
solution as well and
for these particles they
also have very important
protein component right variety
of apoproteins and some
of the apoproteins they
just kind of associate
on the peripheral of the
particles but other apoproteins
kind of buried in the
the phospholipid layers
and just dive a little bit
deeper into the structure
or property of the different
lipoprotein particles
and these different lipids
like triglycerides they
actually have relatively low
densities but in comparison
the protein component of
the lipoprotein and they
tend to have higher
higher densities right so
therefore the more triglycerides
or cholesterol a particle
has the lower is the
intensity. The converse is
also true, right? So there's
more protein component,
the density tend to be higher.
And in the lab, these
different lipoprotein
particles can be separated
by electrophoresis
or the density gradient
centrifugation, right?
So therefore, these
assays or these tools can
be used to separate
them. Therefore, we can
qualify, you know,
how much of each
family of lipoprotein
in the blood.
So here's a quick summary
about the function
of the different
lipoproteins, right? So again,
first these different
lipoproteins to help solubilize
the insoluble lipids so
that making them easier to
be transported in the blood
and also these particles
facilitate the transport
of both the lipid from
the diet as well as the
endosin synthesized lipid and
there's a couple of major
families of lipoprotein
particles for example for
the one family is called
color microns these color
microns and their job is mainly
to transport the dietary
the lipid from our diet
into a variety of tissues
and organs right so in
addition that you'll learn
in the vitamin lecture
And there's a group of
vitamins, they're called
fat-soluble vitamins,
which suggest that
they're very hydrophobic.
And these vitamins can also
be absorbed together
with the dietary lipids.
And not surprisingly,
they also get transported
by carbomicrons to different
tissues and organs.
And there's also a family
of lipoprotein called very
low density lipoprotein,
in short for VLDL, right?
And you probably all heard
about the LDL, it stands
for low density lipoprotein.
lipoprotein. I'm sure
you all heard about the HDLs,
high-density lipoproteins.
And for the VLDL, LDL,
and HDLs, they mainly play
a role in transporting different
lipids that endosinates
synthesize to a variety
of tissues and organs.
And in addition, that
LDL has a special task to
deliver the cholesterols
from liver to different
tissues and organs and
the HDL function to
transport the cholesterols
from peripheral tissue
and back to the liver
for variety of our reuse.
So this table is a nice
table listed different
properties of
different lipoproteins,
right? So, for example,
as you can see here,
from chylomicrons to
HDL, the molecular weight
is, you know, decreased
dramatically, right?
And similarly with the density
and from the chylomicrons
is with the lower density
because it contains
a lot of triglycerides and
cholesterols, right? And
on the other end is high
-density lipoprotein, or HDL,
because it contains less
lipid, but more proteins.
And in terms of the
size, similarly, color
micron, because it's
relatively low dense, it
has the largest size.
And again, on the other
side, the HDLs, they
are relatively small.
So here shows the kind
of, again, the structure,
a diagram of the different
lipoproteins. And
we want to dive a little
bit deeper about the
apoproteins, right? So
again, as we discussed,
the shell of the
different lipoproteins are
made up mainly of
the phospholipids and
different lipids get
packaged inside the
phospholipid balls in
the hydrophobic cores.
The apoprotein, the
protein part of the
lipoprotein play a few
very critical functions.
And some of them
function as the structure
component, as you'll see
in the next few slides,
that the package of the
lipoprotein and start
with the proteins,
and then the different
lipids get load on to
the protein component.
And other lipoproteins
can actually
regulate the enzyme activities,
you'll see again in
the next few slides.
and some of these
lipoproteins actually function
as ligands for different
receptors on different
cell types so that they
can you know get recognized
by different cells and
this is a very nice table
summarize all the
different lipoproteins
right and I use the red
arrows to highlighting
the few very
important apoproteins
that you really need
to be familiar with.
All right, so again,
there's actually three
major pathways for the
lipoprotein metabolism.
And the first one is colomicron.
Again, the colomicron
pathway is mainly to
transport the lipids from the
diet to liver and peripheral
tissues. And for the
VLDL, LDL pathway, and they
mainly transport the lipids
or cholesterols that
synthesize inside the body or
inside the cells and to
different tissues and organs.
And for the HDL pathway,
it mainly transports
the cholesterols from
the peripheral tissue
back to the liver
so that it can be used
for other purposes.
All right, so first
we want to discuss a
little bit more about
the chylomicron pathways.
And this diagram kind
of illustrate, you
know, the process that,
you know, we absorb and
transport the lipids
from the dyes, right?
Again, presumably you have
a balanced meal, right? In
your meals, you know, it
has plenty of sugar, have
plenty of amino acid, and
also have plenty of lipid
right as for the lipid they
are mainly get absorbed in
the small intestines right
so in the small intestines
uh the tg uh get first uh
digested you know roughly
and release some free
fatty acid and also release
the two monoacylglycerols
and these uh component that
easily get absorbed by
the small intestine cells.
So once these get absorbed
by the small intestine
cells, and they repackaged
back into the TGs, and
TGs and other lipids then
get packaged into the
column microns, and column
microns then deliver
them into liver or into
other tissues and organs.
So, how the different colon
microns get synthesized,
right, so most of the, all
the colon microns actually
get synthesized, not
surprisingly, in the intestinal
epithelium cells, right,
again, the major task for
colon microns is to deliver
the lipids from the dye.
And one of the
key apoprotein for
colonomicron is called
ApoB48, right? This
protein actually gets
produced in the ER.
And this is actually
a very interesting
protein in terms of how
the cells make ApoB48.
So the ApoB48 protein
is encoded by the
gene called B
-apoprotein genes, right?
But if the whole B-apoprotein
gene gets transcribed
and translated, it
actually produces a larger
protein, right? But
for the ApoB48, the 48,
that means only 40%, 48%
of the B apoprotein genes
get translated, right?
So how does that cell do
that? So it turns out
after the transcription,
right?
So there's a gene
editing process added in
the cells that want
to make ApoB48, right?
by converting a c into
a u and that editing
creating a stop code right
so therefore the translation
basically stop in the
middle of the messenger
rna right so therefore
the protein get translated
uh is only containing
48 of the amino acids
supposed to you get a full
length proteins Right.
But, you know, in the liver,
the messenger RNA, they
do get fully translated.
Right. Therefore, producing
this 100 percent of
the ApoB protein and
therefore is called ApoB
100. And we'll see that
in the next few slides.
All right. So back
to the chylomicrons.
Right. So once the
ApoB48 protein gets made,
and then a variety of lipids
get loaded on to the ApoB48.
And this process
actually facilitated by
another protein called
microsomal triglyceride
transfer protein.
Again, from the name,
you can see that this
is basically to help to
transfer the TGs to the
ApoB48. And it's a long name,
and the short version
is called MTP or M-TTP.
And because it's an
important function of MTP,
that for certain
individuals, if
they have mutation
in the MTP genes,
and these individuals are
going to have problems
in terms of making the
color microns. So that
leads to a clinical
disease called A-beta. Beta
basically referred to
the ApoB48 protein and
apoproteinemia. Again,
we'll discuss that in a
little bit more detail in
the different lectures.
So once packaged, all
the lipids get loaded
into the 8-column
microns. Column microns
then get secreted first
into the lymphatic
system. and eventually
they're going to enter
the blood system through
the thoracic duct.
So, we see these
slides already.
Once columnicrons got
made, they actually
need a mature system
process, right? So the
maturation of the
climate microns refer to,
they need to pick
up a couple of
extra apoproteins
from the HDL, right?
So these apoproteins,
including the apoc2,
which is actually an
activator of lipase,
right? as well as
ApoE. ApoE actually
functions as a ligand
that can be recognized
by different cellular
receptors, right?
So after the calomicron pick up
these two apoproteins from HDL,
and then they get delivered
into peripheral tissues
and organs for example
muscles adipose tissues right
and at the kind of
intersection of the different
peripheral tissue at the
blood vessel and their anchors
lipase called lpl lipoprotein
lipase right lipase its
function is to hydrolyze a
lipid right so it hydrolyzed
the tg and released the
free fatty acid into these
peripheral tissues
interestingly that the insulin
actually can stimulate the
activities of the lpl which is
not surprising again
dispersely after balanced meal
it has a lot of excess of
lipids and your insulin
level is high after balanced
meal and stimulate a variety
of process that related
to the lipid metabolism.
And one of them is to
activate the LPL that
facilitate the digestion
of lipid, right?
And it's also not surprising
that you can find a lot
of LPL in the tissue organs
that need a lot of lipid.
And as I mentioned, the
apoprotein, apoc2, is a
critical activator to regulate
the activities of LPL.
So after, you know, the
lipid gets transferred from
calomicron into the
peripheral tissue, and the
chalomicron become the
chalomicron remnants, right?
So, you know, leftover of the
metabolism of chalomicrons.
And these chalomicron
remnants can be then
taken up by livers,
by binding to certain
receptors on the
surface of palocytes.
And if you're curious
about, you know,
how the LPL catalyzed
the reaction,
so lpl basically you add
three water molecule and break
down the easter bonds and
release three free fatty
acids at the same time and
generate glycerols right and
glycerols as you recall
from the gluconeogenesis
lecture can function as a
precursors for gluconeogenesis
So, see a few more words
about the fate of the
colomicron, right, again,
you know, after lose the
different lipids, colomicron
become the colomicron
remnants, and because it has
lost a lot of lipids, and
it decreases in size, but
increase in the density,
right, and for the The
apoprotein, again, the
activator of LPL, returns
to the HDLs for further use.
And the chylomicron
reminence can
be taken up by the hepalocytes.
The ApoE protein is still
part of the chylomicron
reminence. And the ApoE
is recognized by the ApoE
receptor on the surface
of hepalocytes. right so
once get recognized a
undergo endocytosis and the
endocytic vesicles subsequently
fused with the lysosome
again lysosome contain
a lot of enzyme that
can digest lipid sugar amino
acid And the content of
these vesicles that can
be digested and reused by
the liver for a variety
of biosynthesis process.
So nothing gets wasted.
All right.
You know, again, because the
critical process in terms
of absorb the fat and
transport the fat and deliver
them to different peripheral
tissues. in case you know
there's certain defect in
the process and that's going
to lead to a variety of
human disease for example
you know if the individual
has problems to absorb the
fat and that leads to the
fat malabsorption clinical
scenarios right and the
possible causes for the for
this scenario for example
because pancreas need to secrete
a variety of lipase right
to digest the lipid and
if the pancreas has problems
and the lipids are going
to be reduced right so
therefore the individual have
problem digesting lipids
and as we discussed in the
cholesterol and bowel cell
lecture the the bowel source
of critical detergent function
to solubilize the lipids
so that the lipase can
easily digest these lipids.
Again, if you have
problems, you synthesize or
secrete bile acid, then
that could lead to the fat
metabolism problems. And
because small intestine is
a major site that these
lipids from the diet get
absorbed. If the individual
has intestinal disease,
that could lead
to the problems.
And one of the clinical
manifestations for the
fat malabsorption is
that you can find a lot
of these bulky lipids or
fatty acids in the stews.
right leads to the
so-called uh sitoria
clinical manifestations
and as I mentioned before
some of the fat soluble
vitamins like vitamin
d e a k they are
get absorbed and
transported to different
tissue organs also by
the chalarmic pathways
right so therefore
these patients that you
know have deficiency to
absorb the fat and they
tend to also have deficiency
in terms of absorbing
enough fat soluble
vitamins all right so
that's chylomicron now we're
going to switch gears and
discuss the vldl ideal
intermediate density
lipoprotein ldl and hdl
So these pathways
mainly try to deal with
the indulgently
synthesized lipid, right?
So, for example, VLDL is
synthesized mainly
in the liver.
VLDL, once they get
synthesized, they get secreted
into the hepatic veins
as a nascent VLDL, right?
Nascent suggesting that
there's a maturation
process, right? So during
the maturation process,
VLDL pick up ApoE and
ApoC2, again, similar to
the colon micron, from
HDL. Now they become
the mature VLDL. So
again, the VLDL help to
carry the lipids,
synthesize from liver, and
deliver them to the
peripheral tissues for energy
use or for a variety of
biosynthesis process.
So, the packaging
of VLDL also needs
apoprotein, right?
So, in this case,
the apoprotein is
called ApoB100, right?
And, as you see the
slides before, instead of
having this RNA editing,
creating a stop codon,
and generating the
ApoB48, which is required
to assemble a packaging,
the color microns,
in this case no
RNA editing taking
place right so the
therefore the full
apol b apol protein
gene get transcribed and
then translated so you
have 100 it means 100 of
the protein right so
that's what the apol b 100
means so similar to the
assembly of colic micron
assembly of vldl also
requires the protein mtp
right so mtp uh facilitate
the loading of lipids
onto the april b100
right therefore form the
vldl right so similarly
uh the lpl and help
to digest and release
the TGs from VLDL.
So, let's see this one already.
So,
once, again, similar
to the column microns,
when the VLDL reach
the peripheral tissues,
the TGs get digested by
the LPL and release the
free fatty acid, which
get absorbed by different
tissues and organs
right so once vl dl lose
these tgs and it become
a vl dl remnant right
again left leftover of
vl dl or they become the
ideal right intermediate
density lipoproteins.
So IDL can be, you
know, taken up by the
livers, right? So IDL is
right here and metabolized
from the VLDL and
they can be, you know,
taken up by the livers,
right? Again, by
associated with the
cell surface receptors.
But the IDL can also
become VLDL, right?
So one, they can acquire
more cholesterol.
Once the IDL acquire more
cholesterol and they become
the LDL right and for
the metabolism LDL right
and they can deliver the
cholesterols to different
peripheral tissues as we're
talking about cholesterol
actually has very important
physiological functions
right for example as a
membrane component or a
precursor to synthesize
other biomolecules, right?
And in addition,
the LDL can also be taken
out by livers, right, is
to recycle and reuse the
contents within the LDLs.
And I'm sure you probably
know the LDL is one of the
problems that cause the
atherosclerosis, right? So one
of the reasons is that the
ldl are prone to be oxidized
right the oxidized ldl and
the cell recognize that
damaged ldl as a problem
and is taken up by the
macrophages right eventually
macrophages become foam cells
this is one of the
causes of atherosclerosis
as you'll see in a
different lectures
Alright, so we want to
see a few more words about
the LDL receptors, because
again, the function of
LDL receptors is help to
take up the LDL particles.
And you can find
LDL receptors in a
variety of tissues and
organs. As we said,
liver has a lot of
LDL receptors also.
And this diagram shows
the structure of the LDL
receptors. LDL receptor
is an integral membrane
protein. It has certain
domains that get anchored
on the cytoplasmic
membranes. And the LDL can
recognize the ApoB100 and
ApoE and through its N
-terminus regions that
protruded outside the cells.
So, you know, LDL
receptors, right, these
green icons, and they
recognize the ApoB100
or ApoE on the surface
of the LDL, right?
So the complex then go
through the endocytosis,
right? So these
endocytosed vesicles.
You know, some of
the LDL receptors can
go back and recycle
to the cell surface.
And others of the
endosome can fuse with the
lysosome, right? And
again, lysosome has a lot
of enzyme, lipase, you
know, enzyme digest,
sugar and amino acid and
release all these components
and they can be used for
variety of biosynthesis and
as you recall you know
many of the solid plasmid
membrane or other membrane
structure also contains the
free cholesterols right
in order to prevent these
cholesterols that are released
from the addosomes that
from the originated from the
ldls and these cholesterols
can be uh easterfies right
so this enzyme called
acyl coa cholesterol acyl
transferase right again from
the name the analyte the
enzyme catalyzed the reaction
that transfer acyl group
to the hydroxy group of the
cholesterols right and
that become a cholesterol
easter. And this is the strategy
to keep the cholesterols
out of the plastic
membranes, you know,
to avoid messed
up the properties.
And interestingly,
the LDL receptor
can also be
regulated, you know,
in the similar process by
the protein, if you recall,
SREVP, right?
You know, SREVP play a
critical role in terms of
regulating the cholesterol
biosynthesis, and here the
SRE protein can also
regulate the LDL receptors.
And one of the diseases
related to the VLDL or LDL
process pathway is the so
-called Neiman-Pickett type C
disease. disease, and this
is because the individuals
has deficiency in terms of
synthesizing some enzyme
for the lysosome, right?
And if lysosome has, you
know, not enough enzyme,
for example, to digest the
lipids and cholesterols, and
these lipids and cholesterols
can build up in the lysosome,
right? leads to cell
death affecting different
tissues and organs all right
so last part of the lecture
I'm going to discuss
how the hdl do the reverse
cholesterol transportation
and relatively to color
micron vldl and h ldl
scientists do try
to understand the
details of the metabolism
of HDL particles.
So you wouldn't be
surprised that some of
these get modified in
the next couple of years.
But anyway,
what we know about
HDL is some of them
can be synthesized
in the liver and
intestines. And similar
to VLDL caromicron,
and when the HDL are
first synthesized,
they are called nascent HDL.
Because nascent HDL
is made up mainly of
phospholipids against the
shell of the particle,
and contain a lot of
apoproteins and its density
is pretty high. it's actually
in the if you observe
under the microscope it
shows the disc shaped
but as the uh hdl acquire
more triglycerides or
cholesterol from vldl and
they become mature hdl
right which is also
called hdl3 um its density
increases uh sorry decreases
right and the shape
become a globular shaped right
and for the one
that has a lot of
cholesterols and they
also called hdl2 so the
major function of hdl
is that they function to
transport the
cholesterols and pick them
up in the peripheral
tissues and transfer
them transport them
back into the livers.
So how does it do that,
right? So one thing that
the for the HDL to pick
up the cholesterol from
the peripheral tissues
is facilitated by another
protein called ABC1. ABC1
is an ATPase protein.
ABC1 basically help to
flip the cholesterol
that uh in the inner lip
lift right inner lifted
and basically it's the side
of the cytoplasmic side
the outer lifted of the
membrane uh is facing the
extracellular space so that abc1
basically move the cholesterol
from the inner leaflet
and flip them to the outer
leaflet, right? So that way,
HDL from the outside can
pick up the cholesterols,
right? So not surprisingly,
you know, if an individual
has gene mutations on the
ABC1s, and then it cannot
flip the cholesterols
efficiently, and that
leads to the accumulated
or increased cholesterol
in the peripheral tissues
and that disease is
called tangier disease and
again we're going to
discuss this disease in a
different lectures so
after hdl pick up the free
cholesterols and they
utilized two enzyme one is
called let's just say
cholesterol acyl transferase
right again from the name
this enzyme basically
add a cell group to the
cholesterol molecule
and this is activated
by april protein
called april a1 on
the hdl right so once
The HDL-acquired cholesterol
is able to activate the
LCET and then LCET as a
group to the cholesterol.
In addition, it also
requires another protein
called cholesterol
easter transfer proteins.
And the kind of the diagram
for these two enzymes
is shown here, right? again
for the LCET a transfer
a cell group from the
phospholipid lechicin
and attach that to the
hydroxy group therefore form
the cholesterol Easter's
right but for the
cholesterol Easter transfer
protein it basically
facilitate the exchange of
TG and cholesterol Easter
between vldl and hdl so
and after the hdl pick up
a lot of cholesterols
right and it deliver them
to the livers right the
way it does that is by a
bad recognize the cell
surface receptor a different
one on the hepatocytes
called scavenger receptors,
right? So that
process is kind of
similar to the VLDL
carbomicrons in a
way, but the
differences between how
HDL transfers its content
or cholesterol to the liver
is that it doesn't go
through the endocytose, right
so which means the whole
HDL particles doesn't get
into the liver cells
right it only transfer the
cholesterol and cholesterol
easter through the scavenger
receptors into the cells right
again only the cholesterol
get passed along to the
livers but the rest of
the HDL particles actually
dissociate and re-enter the
circulation all right so
with that this is kind of
a nice diagram to summarize
different plasma protein
this slides again also
summarize the different function
and metabolism of different
lipoprotein all right so
finally we will also want
to discuss us the last
lipoprotein particles and this
one is called lipoprotein a
with a little a right in
short for lpa the interesting
thing with the lpa is if
you look at the structure of
the lpa right so this is
what the apoprotein part of
the lpa look like right apol
little a So this apol little
a and the whole particle
is nearly identical to the
LDL except the apol little
a is conjugated to the apol
B100 of the LDL by a cysteine
disulfide bond. Right.
And another interesting
thing is that if
you look at the
diagram, all kind of the
structure feature of the
ApoA is actually similar
to another protein
called plasminogen.
Right.
And the major function
of plasminogen is it's a
precursor of plasmin that
helps to degrade fibrin,
which is a major component
of the blood clot.
And the interesting
clinical observation is that
the high level of LPA
actually correlating with the
increased risk of different
coronary heart disease.
And for some individuals
the high level of LPA is
associated with their
genetics. And for others,
if they kind of eat a lot
of trans-fat containing
food, that could lead to
their increased level of
LPA, right? The exact
mechanism of how increased
level of LPA with the
heart disease is not sure.
But one of the hypotheses
is that because the similar
structure of ApoA with
the plasminogen, that it
might interfere with the
dissolving of the plot
clock. So that eventually
leads to the heart disease.
And interestingly,
one of the vitamins,
niacin or vitamin B3,
has been showing in the
clinic that it can
reduce the level of LPA.
But how does that,
it's still unknown.
So with that, this is
the end of the lecture.
again you know here's
the summary slides help
you to guide to study
this particular lectures
all right thank you very much